[MUSIC PLAYING]
DAVID MALAN: All right.
This is CS50, Harvard
University's Introduction
to the Intellectual
Enterprises of Computer Science
and the Art of Programming.
My name is David Malan, and I actually
took this class myself some years ago,
but I almost didn't.
It was my first year in
college and my roommates
and I were living in Matthews
Hall, for those familiar.
[CHEERING]
Nice, Matthews.
Our claim to fame, actually, at the
time was that our room was literally
Matt Damon's just three years' prior.
So onward from that.
But my first year, I didn't
really have the nerves
to set foot in this classroom,
let alone computer science.
In fact, for me, computer
science, and CS50 in particular,
was very much this class to beware.
Like, I was kind of
comfortable with computers,
but I certainly wasn't among those
more comfortable with computers.
And so I shied away my first year.
Instead, I actually took a whole
lot of classes in government.
In fact, in high school, I
was really enjoying history.
I loved this constitutional
law class that I
took my senior year of high school.
And so I figured, OK, if that's
what I liked in high school
and if that's where my
comfort zone was, that's
probably what I should
be doing in college.
And so I essentially declared as my
concentration or major government
for the first year, year
and a half of school.
But my sophomore year when I was living
actually in Mather House instead.
OK, no one from Mather.
In Mather House instead, it was--
I sort of followed some
friends, I think the first week
of class in September of that
year to a class called CS50.
And honestly, once I stepped
foot in that classroom,
the professor at the time was
a famous computer scientist
by the name of Brian
Kernighan, now at Princeton.
Like, I was hooked.
And literally would I go back thereafter
on Friday evenings when, at the time,
problem sets were released
and sit down at 7:00,
8:00 PM on Friday nights
and dive into homework.
Which isn't necessarily
something we recommend, per se.
But for me, it was like this sign that,
wow, I've sort of found my calling.
I found my classmates here on campus.
And that's not going to
be the case for everyone.
Certainly, we have no expectations that
after taking one computer science class
that you will or might
want to take others.
But what's so empowering about
computer science and CS50
in particular is it's so
applicable to the broader world,
whether you're in the arts, humanities,
social sciences, natural sciences,
or beyond, it's just so applicable the
concepts and the practical programming
skills with which you will
exit a class like this.
Now it's going to be challenging along
the way, and indeed, I put in my time
back in the day, and even
I did find it challenging.
And here, for instance, is a
photograph of a very famous MIT hack,
so to speak, from down the
road, whereby it communicates
that getting an education from MIT is
like trying to drink from a fire hose.
Which is to say there's going to be so
much information, like so much new stuff
that certainly on any
given day of the week,
you're not going to be able to absorb
all of it that first time around.
But at the end of the day, it's through
that challenge, putting the time in,
that the returns are therefore just so
much higher at the end of the course.
And indeed, will you walk out of the
course with a much better understanding,
not only of computer
science and programming,
but ultimately how to teach yourself
new technologies and beyond.
For the next three plus months,
will we have teaching fellows,
teaching assistants, course
assistants, and myself by your side
guiding you through
the course's material.
But the goal by term's end is to take
those and leave those training wheels
off so that you're well-equipped
to go teach yourself
new ideas beyond the class itself.
Take comfort, though, in knowing
that most CS50 students have never
taken a CS course before, and
indeed, as per the syllabus,
what ultimately matters in this
course is not so much where
you end up relative to your
classmates but where you end
up relative to yourself when you began.
And when you began is thus today.
And so consider just how
comfortable or uncomfortable
you are with computing, let alone
computer science and programming,
particularly if you've never explored
either in a classroom before,
and consider the delta just a few
months from now that will really
describe how far you have come.
And that is all that
matters, not how much
the student to the left or the right,
in front or behind you right now, knows.
With that said, let me add some
additional inspiration, if I may.
Here's a photograph of my own very first
homework assignment in CS50 from 1996,
and I will draw your
attention to the fact
that even though this is a so-called
hello world program that we'll
play with ourselves next week, it is
pretty much literally the shortest,
easiest program you can write in
a programming language called C.
I still somehow got minus
2 on my very first homework
assignment, which is to say, we're all
going to make mistakes along the way.
But the goal will be to learn and
enjoy that process here on out.
At the end of the day,
too, like me, you'll
exit with your own
proudly held high took
CS50 t-shirt as is our tradition too.
With that said, there are so many
other traditions within CS50,
both on campus and off.
And in particular, do we try in CS50 to
provide not only the academic support
structure that you might
want going through the class,
but also a collective
shared community experience.
Which is to say in just a few days
we'll start off the term formally
with CS50 Puzzle Day, which
is not only an opportunity
to get together with friends,
with pizza and prizes
and also logic puzzles of sorts, but
really to send the message that computer
science itself is not about
programming, it's not about C,
it's not about Python, it's not
about programming languages per se,
but about problem solving, ever more so
collaboratively with other smart people
by your side in this class or beyond.
And indeed, are there, toward the
end of the semester, reinforcements
of the same by way of a little something
that we call the CS50 Hackathon, which
will be an opportunity overnight to
dive into your own final projects,
the capstone of this course,
thereafter followed by the CS50 fair,
which will be a campus wide
exhibition for students, faculty,
and staff across campus of your very own
final projects, be it your very own web
app or mobile app or anything else
you decide to create by term's end.
And indeed, the objective
at the end of the day,
truly with that final
project in particular,
is going to be to create for
yourselves, for your classmates,
for attendees, something that we
didn't even teach you how to do.
And indeed, that will signal ultimately
that you're indeed on your way
and ready.
Toward that end, thought we would
give you a sense of CS50's past
by way of this short
video, if we could dim
the lights, that paints a picture
of all that awaits here and beyond.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
[MUSIC PLAYING]
[END PLAYBACK]
DAVID MALAN: All right, so welcome
aboard to CS50 and computer science
itself.
So what is computer science?
Well, put simply, it's
the study of information.
Like, how do you represent
it and how do you process it.
But more fundamentally, what
we'll teach you in this class
is computational thinking.
That is to say, the application
of ideas from computer science
to problems of interest to us within the
class and problems of interest to you
after the class.
And so at the end of the day,
what computer science really
is is about problem solving, ergo
that sort of global applicability.
And by problem solving, we
mean something quite simple.
In fact, we can distill it as
follows with this mental image.
This is problem solving.
You've got some problem to
solve, thus known as the input
that you want to solve.
And the goal, of course,
to problem solving
is to actually produce a solution.
So the output in this model
would be the solution.
The interesting part ultimately is going
to be in how you process that input
and turn it into that output,
ergo solving problems.
But before we can do that, we all
kind of have to agree how to represent
sent these inputs and
outputs, especially
if we want to do it in a standardized
global way using literally computers,
be them laptops, desktops,
phones, or most any other kind
of electronic device nowadays.
So how can we do that?
Well, there's different ways to
represent information in the world.
For instance, if I were to take
attendance old school style, maybe
in a smaller room, I might
do 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7,
and so forth and just count
people on my human hands.
That's actually known as unary
notation, otherwise mathematically known
as base one, because you're
using your fingers literally
in this model as digits.
But a little quick question.
How high can you count
with one human hand?
Five is incorrect if you use a
different base system than one.
So it's obviously correct if you're just
using unary and just counting 1, 2, 3,
4, 5.
But I dare say I can come up with
more patterns in my human hand
alone that would enable me, without
a second hand or a couple of feet,
to count higher than five.
In fact, maybe for
those more comfortable,
how high could you actually count
on a single human hand, perhaps?
So 31, believe it or not, is,
in fact, the correct answer.
But why?
Well, here I initially
started pretty naively.
1, 2, 3, 4, 5.
And I just combined all of my fingers
and counted the collective total.
But what if I'm a little
more clever and take into
account the pattern
of fingers that go up.
So maybe this is still zero.
This is one.
But now maybe we just agree
universally that this is two.
Even though it's just my
single pointer finger.
Maybe we all just agree that this
is three with two fingers up.
Maybe we agree that this is
often offensive with just one
middle finger up, but
this would then be four.
This could then be five.
This could then be six.
This could be seven.
And if I keep permuting my fingers
in this way-- allow me to spoil it--
this would be, in fact, 31.
But again, why?
But the difference here is that
we're no longer using unary or base
one as a mathematician would
say, but rather base two.
Because if we take into account
not just the total number
of fingers that I'm using, but whether
each finger is down or up being
therefore in two potential states.
Down, up, A, B, black,
white, however you
want to distinguish those
two states of the world,
you're now operating what's called
base two, and perhaps more familiarly,
even if you're not a computer person per
se, this is the so-called binary system.
And odds are, even if you're not
a computer science person at all,
you probably generally know that
computers only understand or speak
what alphabet, so to speak?
So ones and zeros, zeros and ones,
otherwise known as the binary system.
And in fact, there's a term of
art here that's worth noting.
When you're using zeros and ones, which,
of course, are a total of two digits,
you have binary digits, so
to speak-- bi implying two,
which means there's two
possibilities, zero or one.
If we actually get rid of some of these
letters and then join these two phrases,
here you have a technical
term that is a bit.
A bit is just a binary digit,
which is to say it's a zero or one.
And this is in contrast,
of course, with the system
you and I know as the decimal system.
Dec implying 10, because
in the real world
you and I daily use zero through
nine, which is 10 possibilities.
Computers only use zero and
one, that is to say two bits,
to represent information instead.
So how do we represent this
information, especially when at the end
of the day what we're using are indeed
computers and electronic devices?
Well, if I want to represent zero, I
can actually think of this as analogous
to the physical world.
Maybe I have a light bulb
that's off or on controlled
by a switch that turns it off or on.
So you can think of a binary
digit that is a zero as really
just being a light bulb that is off.
By contrast, if you think of a one
in the digital world as, of course,
being the second of
two possibilities, you
can think of that in the human or
analog world, the physical world,
as being a light bulb that is on.
And in fact, what's inside of your
Mac, your PC, your Android phone,
your iPhone are millions of
tiny little light switches
known as transistors that just can
be turned on or off, on or off.
And essentially, you can use those
transistors to store information
because if you want to store a zero,
you turn one of those switches off.
If you want to store a one, you
turn one of those switches on.
Of course, that sort of
invites the question, well,
how do we count higher than zero or one?
Well, we would seem to
need to use more than just
maybe a single bit, a single light bulb.
So if we wanted to count higher
than, for instance, zero or one,
why don't we go ahead and maybe do this?
So just so I have some
place to put these,
let me borrow some of our
actual physical light bulbs
here from the stage.
And let me propose that now, with three
bits on the stage, three light switches,
three transistors, whatever metaphor
you're most comfortable with, this
is how a computer would represent a
zero, because all of them are off.
So it's off, off, off.
But if a computer wanted to count
to one, we could do naively this.
We could turn this on.
If the computer wanted to turn
represent two, we could do this.
And if a computer wanted to
represent three, we could do this.
But I'm kind of painting
myself into a corner
and not using these light
bulbs as cleverly as I could,
because at the moment I've
only counted as high as three.
So if I want to count to
four, to five, to six,
I'm going to need more
and more light bulbs.
Can we be a little more clever?
Well, again, someone else who's
among those more comfortable, what's
the spoiler here?
How high using binary
zeros and ones could I
count with three light bulbs total?
In back?
Yeah.
So seven here is the answer.
And if that, too, you're
sort of wondering,
how are people figuring out 31 and 7?
That's the goal at hand here.
So let me do this.
Let me turn all of these off again so
that my three light bulbs or switches
again represent zero.
And the first one's easy.
This is how a computer would
represent the number one.
It would be on, off, off.
How, though, is a computer
going to represent two?
Well, just like my
proposed finger example.
Let's do this.
Let's turn this one off and this one on.
That is how a computer
would represent two.
By saying off, on, off.
In other words, 010 would be the
way to pronounce it digitally.
What if I instead want
to represent three?
That's how on my finger I
did this, with two fingers.
Well, I'm going to turn this one on.
This is three.
Now, this will, for those less
comfortable, be non-obvious.
This now is how I would
represent the number four.
This is how I would represent five.
This is how I would represent six.
And this, as per the spoiler,
is how I would represent seven.
So perhaps very non-obvious
what it was I just did
or why I chose those patterns.
But I dare say if you rewind in your
mind's eye or literally later on video,
you'll find that I actually did show you
eight distinct patterns of light bulbs.
The first one was off, off, off.
The last one was, on, on, on.
And there were another
six total in between then.
Well, wait, why seven?
Well, if you start counting at zero and
I claim there's eight possibilities,
you can only count from zero
to seven, as we will soon see.
So how are these patterns
coming about and what is it
that our computers are actually doing?
Well, it's actually doing something a
little like this, quite like in decimal.
So in the human world,
you and I are very
much in the habit of using base
10, zero through nine, a.k.a.
Decimal.
Well, how do we use it
instinctively as humans?
Well, what's this number
obviously on the screen?
123.
But why is it 123?
Like, for years you
haven't really thought
about why this pattern of
symbols or digits on the screen,
one, two, three, represents
mathematically this number
that you know obviously as 123.
But if you rewind to
grade school, odds are,
like me, you were taught that the
rightmost digit is in the ones column,
this second digit is in the tens column,
this digit is in the hundreds column,
and so forth.
So even though none of us have
to do this math explicitly,
what you're instantly doing
is 100 times 1 plus 10 times
2 plus 1 times 3, which
gives you 100 plus 20 plus 3.
Oh, that's why it is 123, because
these digits in this order
have that significance.
The digits to the left have
more weight, so to speak,
than the digits to the right.
So what can we take away from this?
Well, let's generalize it first
as just any three digit number.
So number, number, number.
The ones column, the tens
column, the hundreds column.
But there's some math going on there,
and it's not particularly sophisticated.
Those are actually powers of 10.
So 10 to the 0, 10 to the 1, 10 to the
2, and there's your decimal system.
Because the base in this
value is a 10, that's
because there's 10 possibilities
for each of those placeholders,
zero through nine.
But in the binary world, in the
world of computers where all they
have are zeros and ones, why?
Because all they have
physically is transistors.
Tiny, tiny, tiny light
bulbs that can be off or on.
If you only have two
digits to play with,
the 10 base should, of
course, become a two base.
And now if we do some math here, 2
to the 0, 2 to the 1, and 2 to the 2,
you get the ones column, the
twos column, the fours column.
And if we keep going 8, 16,
32, 64, 128 and so forth,
its powers of 2 instead of powers of 10.
But this is to say computers
represent information
in exactly the same way you
and I have since childhood,
but they have fewer
digits at their disposal,
so these columns need to
be weighted differently.
So we can still count from zero
all the way up toward infinity.
So what does this mean?
Well, here we have three
bits on the screen, 000.
If we were to convert this now
mentally or on paper pencil to decimal,
how do we do it?
Well, 4 times 0 plus 2
times 0 plus 1 times 0.
That gives us the mathematical
number you and I know as zero.
That was three light bulbs.
Off, off, off.
Well, what if we turn on one light
bulb all the way on the right?
What decimal number does this
binary number, 001 represent?
Just one, because it's 4
times 0, 2 times 0, 1 times 1.
Here's where things
got more interesting,
even if non-obvious in light bulb
form or even physical hand form.
010 in binary is what in decimal?
Two, because it's 2
times 1 and that's it.
011 in binary is, of course now three.
This is now four.
This is now five.
This is now six and seven.
On, on, on or 111 is the highest
we can count with these three bits.
All right.
So how might a computer
intuitively count as high as eight?
What do you need to do, presumably?
You're going to need to add a bit.
So you need another light
bulb, another switch.
You need more memory, so to
speak, to use nomenclature
with which you're probably familiar.
So in fact, if we change
all of those to zero
but we give ourself one more
bit for a total of four,
that's got to be the eighth
place because there's just
another power of two.
So 1000 is the decimal number eight.
You don't say 1,000 in binary.
You literally say 1000.
But that is the number
you and I know as eight.
And you can keep going up and up and up.
And how then computers with Excel or
any kind of number crunching software
count really high and keep
track of really big numbers?
The computer just throws more and
more transistors at it, more and more
bits to count higher and
higher and higher than this.
It turns out, though, one bit,
three bits, even four bits
aren't that useful in practice
because literally you can count
as high as seven or maybe 15 or 31.
So more commonly, as is commonly known,
is to use a byte of bits instead.
How many bits is in a
byte, for those familiar?
So it's just eight.
Why eight?
It's just more useful than one or
two or three or some other number.
And as an aside, it happens
to be a power of two, which
is just useful electronically as well.
So a byte then is just 8 bits.
And here are those columns I
rattled off off the top of my head.
Here is how a computer would
represent zero in decimal,
but using eight binary digits or bits.
Little trivia.
And again, this is not what
computer science is about,
but it helps to know the lower
bounds and the upper bounds
of these kinds of values.
How high can you count with 8
bits or 1 byte if this is zero?
Yeah.
So it's actually 255.
So if I were to change
all of these zeros to ones
and then do some quick mental
or calculator math, 128 plus 64
plus 32, 16, 8, 4, 2, and 1
would actually give me 255 total.
Plus 0, which gives me
256 total possibilities.
So this is only to say-- this
is not, again, the kind of math
will frequently do,
but you'll commonly see
in the computer world and
programming world powers of two,
numbers like 255, 256.
Why?
Because these are the common units
of measures that systems tend to use.
So let me pause here and see,
with respect to binary, zeros,
and ones, transistors and the like, any
questions or confusion we can clear up?
Oh, really good question.
Why are bits just on or off instead
of maybe sort of 0%, 50%, 100%
by playing with voltages?
So the voltage inference of
yours is actually correct.
That's what computers typically do.
Maybe they use 0-ish volts to represent
0, maybe 5-ish volts to represent 1.
It turns out it's just really
easy to do extremes in computers.
If you start to split that
range of voltage levels,
for those who remember
any of their electricity,
it just gets harder
and harder to be exact.
And if you get things
a little too murky,
you might mistake a zero for
a one or a two or a three.
So it turns out it's just
simpler to use the binary system.
But there do exist computers known
as ternary computers that actually
use three values, zero, one, and
two, which is somewhere, of course,
between binary and decimal.
But you can do different things.
It's just simple on and off.
In case in point, I don't want to really
be dramatic and turn off my computer,
but if I pulled out the power plug,
that could be off, literally, a.k.a.
zero.
Plug it back in, that's a one.
There's just a cleanliness
and simplicity to that.
Other questions or confusion
that we can clear up?
No?
OK.
So if you're in agreement for the moment
that, OK, using just zeros and ones,
we can represent any number
we want from zero on up, let
me propose that we do more useful things
with our computers and our pockets
and desktops and laps
like represent letters,
for the sake of Google Docs,
Microsoft Word, or any kind of text
that we might want to write.
So knowing now that computers only
contain or only use zeros and ones,
and therefore only contain
hardware like transistors,
how could you represent
something like a capital letter
A in English inside of a computer?
Which, of course, is
not a number anymore.
Like, what could we do?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: We could use the
alphabet and then use numbers.
DAVID MALAN: OK, yeah.
So we could take the alphabet
A through Z in English
and we could just assign
each letter A number.
And honestly, that is not
only the correct answer,
it's really the only answer.
Because at the end of
the day, if all you
have are zeros and
ones available to you,
that is the entirety of the
potential solution to this problem.
So it turns out that, yes,
capital letter A, some years ago,
was decided by a bunch of people
in a room shall be represented
with this pattern of zeros and ones.
01000001.
And now, trained as you are
to do a bit of quick binary
math, what decimal number is used
to represent apparently capital A?
So 65, because that's 64
plus 1 plus 1 times 1 is 65.
What is B?
Turns out it's 66.
What is C?
67.
So they kept things simple there on out.
Might have been nice if A
were zero or maybe a were one.
But nope, we're stuck with 65 instead.
But everything after that
is very much predictable.
And in fact, for
lowercase letters, there's
a whole other set of numbers such
as lowercase A happens to be 97,
lowercase B happens to
be 98, and so forth.
But again, this is like CS trivia.
But what's important here is that
there are indeed contiguous from 65
to 66 to 67 on up.
That's something we're going to be able
to leverage beyond the letter A alone.
What is this system?
What is this mapping that
you yourself propose?
It's ASCII, the American Standard
Code for Information Interchange.
And indeed, it was a bunch of Americans
years ago who came up with this system.
Unfortunately, at the time, they only
allocated 7 and eventually 8 bits total
for representing letters, both
uppercase and lowercase, numbers
on the keyboard as well,
punctuation symbols as well.
And so per our conversation a moment
ago, if the Americans in this room,
so to speak, only used 8 bits total,
how many different characters can we
represent with a computer in this story?
So only 255, technically 256 if we,
again, start counting from zero.
So that's not nearly enough to
represent all human languages,
but it is enough to represent at
least English, among some others.
So here, for instance, is a
chart of the ASCII mapping.
And sure enough, if we zoom in on
this column here, 65 is capital A,
66 is capital B, dot, dot, dot
72 is H, 73 is I, and so forth.
So there is a standardized mapping for
at least all of these English letters.
Well, suppose you were to receive
an email or a text message
or like a Google Doc containing
this pattern of zeros and ones.
So 01001000 and so forth and so forth.
So 3 bytes worth.
Three sets of 8 bits.
That is to say 3 bytes, each of which
represents a single letter in ASCII.
What message have you received?
Well, I'll do the math this
time so we don't have to.
Suppose what you really
received was decimal 72, 73, 33.
What message did you just receive?
If you recall the previous chart.
Hi was in fact correct.
Why?
Because H is 72, I is 73.
And wait a minute, 33.
So here's H. Here's I. 33,
if we highlight it instead,
happens to be an exclamation point.
So that is literally what is going
on underneath the hood, so to speak,
when you get a text message today
that literally says in all caps
and an exclamation point, HI!
Your phone has received at
least three bytes, each of which
represents a letter of the alphabet.
Your computer is quickly
doing the mental math
to figure out exactly what
numbers those are and then
looking up in the so-called ASCII
chart in its memories, in some sense,
what letter should you actually
see on the screen there.
And so if you were to
then display that message,
you would see it indeed in English as
opposed to those numeric equivalents.
How else might we use this then?
Well, here again is that chart.
And maybe just to vary things, maybe
take a little pressure off of me
here, why don't we try
spelling something else?
This time a different three letter
word, but maybe eight volunteers.
Could we get a bytes'
worth of volunteers?
And I can sweeten the deal with
some stress balls in exchange.
You just have to be comfortable coming
up on stage and being on the internet.
So yes.
One, two.
How about three, four.
How about five, six, seven.
And how about eight.
Come on up.
A round of applause for our volunteers.
Yep.
[APPLAUSE]
All right.
So what I'm going to
have each of you do is
represent a bit in a particular order.
So if you want to just,
in any order, line
yourselves up here facing the audience.
Come on over.
All right.
And we will have you represent--
well, we got to see who ends up where.
Scooch this way a little bit.
This way, this way.
All right.
So you shall be the ones place and
just hold that in front of you.
Twos place.
Threes.
Fours place.
Eights place.
16, 32, 64, and 128.
And just compress yourselves
a little bit if you could.
So each of these folks represents
a bit in a particular place.
And let's say this.
If you're just standing there
uncomfortably without any hand raise,
we'll assume that you're
representing a zero, quite simply.
If your hand goes up,
though, the audience
should assume that you're
representing a one.
And therefore, what we'll do is
spell out a three letter word,
and on each round of this, you'll
either stay, stay like this,
or you'll raise your hand.
But first, let's actually
meet some of our volunteers
here, starting with position number
one, if you'd like to say your name,
perhaps where you're
from and/or studying.
AUDIENCE: Hi.
My name is Brooke.
I'm from Indiana, and I'm studying
biology and computer science.
DAVID MALAN: Nice.
Welcome.
AUDIENCE: Hi, I'm Becca.
I'm from, like, Maryland, DC area, and
I'm studying electrical engineering.
DAVID MALAN: Welcome.
AUDIENCE: Hi, I'm Addison.
I'm from Maryland.
I'm studying engineering.
AUDIENCE: Hi.
I'm Sharon.
I'm from Rwanda and I'm
studying CS and math.
DAVID MALAN: Welcome.
AUDIENCE: Hi, I'm Grace.
I'm from Alabama and I'm
studying electrical engineering.
DAVID MALAN: Welcome.
AUDIENCE: Hi, I'm Angelina.
I'm from Maryland.
And also, I stay in Matthews.
DAVID MALAN: Nice.
Matthews.
Nice.
[APPLAUSE]
AUDIENCE: And I'm studying
applied math and econ, as well as
environmental science and public policy.
DAVID MALAN: Welcome.
AUDIENCE: I'm Owen Bells and I'm from
rural Virginia and I'm studying CS.
DAVID MALAN: Nice, welcome.
And?
AUDIENCE: My name is Max.
I'm from London.
I'm also staying in Matthews and
I'm studying computer science
and neuroscience.
Thank you.
DAVID MALAN: Welcome aboard as well.
If you're wondering,
too, why I was wearing
these glasses at the start-- so
very common on the internet nowadays
as these POV videos.
So it turns out these Ray-Bans
actually record video footage,
and we have a couple of them, and
we'd thought we would offer them
to a couple of volunteers.
If anyone wants to record their
point of view for everyone here.
And Vlad here is going to help
make sure they're recording.
Second volunteer.
Yes, number two.
All right.
So as Vlad gets those set, on
the backs of your pieces of paper
you have instructions for
the following three rounds.
Each round represents a letter.
The audience participation
part of this is
to actually do the mental math to figure
out what number these volunteers are
representing.
So go ahead and execute round one,
either keeping your hand down or raising
it appropriately.
OK.
What number are our
volunteers here representing?
AUDIENCE: 66.
DAVID MALAN: 66, because
we have a 64 plus a 2.
That then maps to what ASCII letter?
AUDIENCE: B.
DAVID MALAN: B was the first letter.
OK, hands down.
Round two, go.
A little harder.
What's now being represented?
AUDIENCE: 79.
DAVID MALAN: I'm starting to hear it.
79 is in fact correct.
79, because we have a 64 and
an 8 and 4 and 2 and a 1.
So if it's a 79, we
have the ASCII letter O.
So we've got BO, and
then lastly, third round.
Go.
We have 01010111.
What number is this?
AUDIENCE: 87.
DAVID MALAN: 87.
Which spells the letter?
AUDIENCE: W.
DAVID MALAN: W. Which spells the word?
AUDIENCE: Bow.
DAVID MALAN: Not bow.
Take a bow if you could.
All right.
A round of applause for
our volunteers here.
[APPLAUSE]
And come on off this way and help
yourself to a CS50 stress ball.
Thank you to our volunteers.
So this is only to say we've now
agreed on how we can represent numbers
from zero on up.
We've agreed on how we
can represent letters.
But at least letters using
ASCII, and in fact, these
are more than just decoration.
In fact, it's a little bit
of trivia by lecture's end.
If you to come up for your
very own CS50 stress ball,
turns out there are 64 light bulbs
at the foot of the stage here.
If you break them down
into 8 byte or single--
8 bit or single byte chunks,
there's an eight letter word
that happens to be spelled out
today using this here ASCII chart.
So today's mystery is what
exactly is that there word.
But of course, if you have only 8
bits, you can only represent, like,
256 characters, which sounds like
plenty for English, and indeed, it is.
Zero through nine, A through
B, capital and lowercase,
uppercase and lowercase,
as well as punctuation.
But there's so many
other human languages
in the world that have other characters.
For instance, we have not
just the English alphabet
we might see here on
a US English keyboard.
We have accented characters,
we have various Asian languages
have even many more glyphs.
We need more than 256
possible characters.
And so nowadays computers do
not just use 7 or even 8 bits.
They might use 8 bits for some letters,
like all of the English letters.
They might use 16 bits for
certain other languages.
Maybe even 24 or 32 bits.
And fun fact, if you have 32 bits--
and we have more than that on the stage.
If you've got 32 bits,
you can actually represent
as many as 4 billion possible
characters, which is quite a bit.
No pun intended.
So what else can we represent?
Well, the goal of this
system, not just ASCII,
but something known as Unicode,
which is a newer standard,
is to be backwards
compatible with ASCII.
So humans left all of those other
numbers alone, 65, 66, 67 and so forth,
but they added to it a
super set of representations
that maybe are 16, 24, or 32 bits.
The goal being to be able digitally to
represent all human languages, past,
present, and future, and even
through pictograms, things
like smiley faces and the like, even
people, places, things and emotions that
transcend human language.
And in fact, odds are within the past
few minutes or hours, most of you
have used one or more of these here
emoji, these pictograms, which it turns
out are just characters on a keyboard.
You might have to hit a special button
to pull up that form of the keyboard,
but these are just here characters.
And so these emoji have
exploded in popularity
for a number of reasons, one of
which is, my God, what are we
going to do with 4 billion possible
patterns of zeros and ones?
We can start to have some fun
with it and represent things
beyond English and
human languages alone.
Now, as an aside, when
it comes to Unicode,
it turns out Unicode, years ago,
standardized this pattern of 32 zeros
and ones to represent
just one of those emoji.
So emoji tend to use
even more bits here.
Anyone know what decimal number this is?
This is not a fun mathematical exercise.
The spoiler is 4,036,991,106 is the
decimal number that actually represents,
as of present, the most
popular emoji in the world.
Does anyone want to hazard a guess
what emoji this here number represents?
AUDIENCE: Heart.
DAVID MALAN: Heart?
Hearts?
No, but it's actually this
so-called face with tears of joy.
So perhaps think about the frequency
with which you send that one.
And even though it's obviously
a picture on the screen, sure,
it actually is more like a font,
because underneath the hood,
it's indeed just a pattern of
zeros and ones or a decimal number
that the computer is storing.
But the computer, be it Mac OS
or Windows or iOS or Android,
know to display that pattern
as this here picture.
But the pictures might look
different depending on the hardware.
Why?
Because there's companies like Google
and Microsoft and Meta and others
that have their own artists
on staff as employees,
and those artists
interpret the descriptions
like face with tears of joy differently.
So those of you with an Android phone
actually see face with tears of joy
looking a little something like this.
And if you have Telegram, for
instance, installed on your phone,
it's even more animated than that.
It's this here emoji using the
same pattern of zeros and ones.
So different artists render these
here emoji in different ways,
but all they are here are patterns.
Now, for all of the other answers, save
one that was shouted out a moment ago,
this is a sort of cloud diagram
of the most popular emoji as
of a couple of years ago per Unicode,
whereby the size of the emoji
indicates its relative popularity.
So heart, I did here
over here, is indeed
one of the most popular ones as well.
Question?
AUDIENCE: Why do certain
emojis show up [INAUDIBLE]?
DAVID MALAN: Oh, really good question.
Why do certain emoji not show
up on one device or another?
It depends on how
recent the software is.
Pretty much every year the humans
behind the Unicode consortium
release new emoji.
Which is to say they decide
that this other pattern will
represent this new emoji, this other
pattern will represent this new emoji.
And unless you update
your phone, your laptop,
your desktop to the very latest software
and the manufacturer of that device
or software also updates
by hiring an artist
to draw those pictures in their
own fonts, in their own style,
you're going to see usually just
an empty black square or maybe just
a black and white heart instead
of something more colorful.
Really just placeholders,
because, it's as though you
don't have the right
font installed or really,
you have an older version
of that same font installed.
But it's become sort of an annual
tradition that new and more emoji
are released every year, which is among
the reasons why these updates contain
more and more.
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: How do you
represent color in bytes?
DAVID MALAN: That is an amazing segue.
How do you represent color in bytes?
Well, you use RGB, which happens to
be, by coincidence, the next slide.
So let's again, recap.
We know how to represent letters.
We know how to represent numbers.
We can even represent emoji.
But those emoji
technically on the screen
are, of course, composed of colors,
like a whole bunch of yellow
for that there smiley face?
How do computers, then, using only
zeros and ones, represent colors?
Well, by convention, they typically
use a system that, by an acronym,
is called RGB.
Red, green, blue.
And this is to say that a computer, to
represent a single dot on the screen--
maybe this one, this one, this one--
will allocate some number of bits
or some number of bytes to represent the
color of just that, their dot, otherwise
known as a pixel.
You can actually see pixels on your
phone or even on your TV or monitor.
If you go really close, especially
if it's an older monitor,
you can see the tiny little squares.
Each of those has some number of bits
telling the device what color to use.
In particular, these devices typically
use three numbers in total, three bytes.
So that is to say 24 bits per pixel.
And they do this.
If you were to represent a single
dot on the screen using these three
numbers, just by intent
here, this is 72, 73,
33, which in the context of
a text message, an email,
a Google Doc represents,
of course, hi, textually.
What if a computer
uses that same pattern
of zeros and ones, that is the
same pattern of decimal digits,
to represent the color on a screen?
Which is germane if you're
opening an image using Photoshop.
So using a different
piece of software that
knows about colors and
images and not just text.
Well, this would imply that
you want that dot on the screen
to have a medium amount of
red, a medium amount of green,
and a little bit of blue.
Why do I say medium and little?
Well, again, if each of these
numbers is using 8 bits or 1 byte,
the highest we can count,
as we discovered, was 255.
So I'm kind of averaging here.
So 72 at a 255 feels to me
like a medium amount of red.
33 feels relatively little blue.
But if now the computer combines those
wavelengths of light, so to speak,
a medium amount of red,
medium amount of green,
a little bit of blue, what you get
is the color code for a single dot.
And does anyone want to guess what
color roughly this represents,
these three bytes?
AUDIENCE: White.
AUDIENCE: Purple.
DAVID MALAN: Not white, not purple.
AUDIENCE: Brown.
DAVID MALAN: Not brown.
AUDIENCE: Yellow.
DAVID MALAN: Yellow,
in fact, is the answer.
So it represents in a single pixel
roughly this shade here of yellow.
Which is to say, if we look back at
any of those emoji, which, again,
are represented by
patterns of zeros and ones,
but you and I as humans perceive
them as images on the screen--
let me actually go ahead
and zoom and zoom in further
to one such sample emoji.
And when you zoom in far enough or you
put the phone close enough to your face,
you can actually see all
of those little dots known
as pixels, all of the little squares.
And given that so many of
these pixels are yellow,
that is to say that that
pattern of three bytes,
72, 73, 33, is used to
represent this pixel.
Another 3 identical bytes are used
to represent this pixel, this one,
this one, and so forth.
So now if you've taken digital
photos on your phone or a camera,
you're probably generally familiar
from the internet and hardware
today that a photograph is, what,
1 megabyte, 10 megabytes depending
on the resolution of it?
Well, megabyte means millions of bytes.
Where are all of these bytes
inside of these photographs
or these images you're
taking or downloading?
They correspond to every one of
the single pixels on the screen.
There's at least three bytes being used
to represent every one of those dots.
As an aside, bit of a white
lie because nowadays there's
fancy compression software that
can use fewer than that many bytes.
But in general, that's where all of
those bytes, those millions of bytes
are coming from.
So how is that for an answer
to how do we represent colors?
Thank you.
So if we agreed now that
there's this way and perhaps
others to represent
colors, well, how do we
represent not just images, but videos?
Well, videos once upon a time, or
movies, were called motion pictures.
So motion pictures with motion.
Why is that?
Well, it's analogous to growing up.
If you ever played with one of
these picture books-- and in fact,
there's memes nowadays that
have made these popular again,
whereby why you have a whole bunch of
images on individual sheets of paper.
And if you flip through
them fast enough,
your human mind and eyes
perceive it as actual motion,
even though you're just seeing image,
image, image, image, image, image.
But it's so fast, it looks like motion.
That's all a video is on your screen.
That's all a film is on your TV.
It is not in fact, continuous motion.
It's maybe 30 frames or images
per second, maybe 24 frames
or images per second.
Which is to say, we know
how to represent numbers,
we know how to represent
letters, we know how
to represent colors and thus images.
Now we kind of get videos for free
because it's just more of the same.
Use more and more of those patterns.
Why are videos so darn large?
Why are they gigabytes to
download, billions of bytes?
Because there's so many darn images.
30 some odd images per second
in those kinds of videos.
And maybe lastly, just to
top off our multimedia,
how could you represent sound?
Maybe musicians in the room.
How, using only zeros and ones,
could you represent something
as sonorous as music?
Something analog as digital.
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: So each number
corresponds to a frequency.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
So each number that we
store in the computer
could correspond to a
certain frequency, which
has a direct relationship to the
sound or the pitch of a note.
For instance, in the world of
piano and many other instruments,
you've got like your A, your B, your C,
maybe you have sharps and flats as well.
We could just agree,
like the ASCII people
did years ago, to represent
the musical note A, let's use
this pattern, musical note A-sharp,
let's use this pattern and so forth.
But maybe pitch alone or
frequency alone is not enough.
Maybe we need that number,
but maybe a second number
for the volume, the sort of
digital equivalent of how hard
are you hitting the key on the piano.
Maybe a third number for how long
are you holding the key down.
So maybe the pitch and the volume
and the duration, kind of like RGB,
we could use three bytes to represent
every musical note in some piece.
And if we wanted to keep track
of what instrument should
be played by the computer
to sound that music,
well, maybe that's just a fourth
byte or something else as well.
Which is to say, at
the end of the day, all
we have are these zeros and
ones to throw at the problem.
So for now, that's it for
representing information.
We've got our numbers,
we've got our letters,
we've got our colors and images,
our videos, and now sound.
Any questions on how computers,
then, are representing, as promised,
those inputs and outputs
using just zeros and ones?
Yeah, in the middle.
AUDIENCE: The computer
is taking it as input.
DAVID MALAN: Correct.
So the computer is taking as input
at the end of the day, zeros and ones
and is outputting zeros and ones.
However, as we'll learn in this
class, by writing software,
by writing code that understands
those zeros and ones we will enjoy
not just literally
seeing zeros and ones,
we will see A, B, C, we will
see colors, we will see video,
we will hear sounds so long as we
write the code to interpret those zeros
and ones.
And indeed, it's worth
noting now that same pattern
I keep using for an example, 72,
73, 33, how does a computer know?
Is that the message hi?
Is that the color yellow?
Is it a dot in a video alone?
Just depends on the context.
Simply put, if you're opening
that pattern of zeros and ones
with Excel or a calculator
program, odds are
the software will interpret those
three bytes as numbers, of course.
If, though, you open that same
pattern in a text messaging program,
Google Docs, Microsoft
Word, that same pattern
will be interpreted as
a sequence of letters.
Instead, if you open
Photoshop, that same pattern,
you'll probably see a single
dot that happens to be yellow.
Conversely, once you yourself are a
programmer or even better programmer,
you will be able to write in code
how you want the computer to treat
these patterns of zeros and ones.
You can essentially tell the computer,
use this to store a number or a letter
or a color or something else.
That's the power the programmer
themselves have at the end of the day.
Other questions on
representing things with bits?
No?
All right.
So lastly, then, in this middle
of this black box, so to speak,
is the sort of secret
sauce that solves problems,
that converts those inputs to
outputs, those problems to solutions.
So what is an algorithm?
It's really just step by step
instructions for solving some problem.
And indeed, I think back to
my own first time in CS50
where we learned the same from
Professor Brian Kernighan.
And as luck would have it, just had my
25th reunion where we pulled some video
footage from 1996.
And so we're actually fortunate to
have the very first few minutes of CS50
over 25 years ago when I myself took it.
But the lessons back then, as
today, are fundamentally the same.
And what's important, indeed, is to
not only express yourself correctly,
but precisely, as we'll explore today.
This then is Professor
Brian Kernighan, who,
years ago, very memorably introduced
us and my classmates to algorithms
by actually, in class,
shaving his beard.
If we could dim the
lights here for Brian.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
- The other thing that we're
going to talk about in this class
is the notion of an algorithm.
An algorithm is a very precise
description of how to do something.
And the operative word there is precise.
It has to be very, very,
very, very precise.
And the task that I'm
going to do is that I'm
going to trim my beard, which
has gotten out of whack.
[APPLAUSE]
And I brought a variety of things which
one might use to trim beards with.
[LAUGHTER]
[APPLAUSE]
[END PLAYBACK]
DAVID MALAN: So suffice it to
say, I don't have much of a beard.
But I do have this here other technology
known once upon a time as a phone book.
And these phone books, of course,
have lots of information in them.
Happen to be storing numbers
and letters in particular.
For those unfamiliar, they are
storing human's names from A to Z
here in English and associated
with everyone's name is a number.
So even if you've never had occasion
to physically use this kind of device,
turns out it's pretty much equivalent
to the contacts or the address book app
on your iOS phone or your
Android phone as well.
Why?
Because if you pull up
your contacts, of course,
you see some familiar names here
alphabetized by first name or last name.
And if you click on
any of those names, you
reach the person you're
presumably trying to call or text.
Pictured here then is John
Harvard's, whose number here is plus
1-949-468-2750, which you're welcome
to call or text at your leisure.
But here is John Harvard that's partway
through the phone book digitally.
Well, it turns out that
physically in the phone book,
we might use an algorithm,
step by step instructions,
for finding John Harvard in pretty
much the same way as iOS, Android,
Mac OS, Windows, or other
operating systems themselves use.
So I could, when looking for John
Harvard, first name, starting with J,
I could start at the
beginning of the phone book
and start looking page by
page by page for John Harvard.
And if he's there, I can call.
This is an algorithm.
It's indeed step by
step, but that was a bug.
A few pages turned.
But is this algorithm correct?
Step by step, assuming
I'm paying attention.
So yes, if John Harvard is
in here, I will eventually
find him once I get to the J section.
Now, this is a little tedious.
It's going to take a while.
A few dozen, a few hundred pages.
So maybe I could do things a little
smarter from grade school, like 2, 4, 6,
8, 10, 12, 14, 16, and so
forth, going twice as fast.
Is that algorithm correct?
So no, but why?
AUDIENCE: You could miss it.
DAVID MALAN: I could miss him, right?
I could just get unlucky,
really, with 50/50 probability,
because John Harvard could be
sandwiched between two pages.
Now, this isn't a complete
loss, this algorithm.
Maybe what I could do is if I
get past the J section to K,
I could double back
at least one page just
to make sure I didn't miss John Harvard.
So I can still go twice as
fast plus an extra step just
to make sure I didn't mess up.
So the first algorithm
might take as many pages
as there are in the phone book.
So if this phone book has a thousand
pages, in the worst case, if I'm not
looking for John Harvard, but
someone whose name starts with Z,
might take me a thousand
pages to actually get there.
Second algorithm, twice as fast.
Literally, it might take
me 500 plus one step
to get there because
I'm going two at a time,
so as long as I indeed fix that bug.
But what we used to do
back in the day and what
your phone is doing
today, albeit digitally,
is going roughly to the middle of the
phone book, looking down and realizing,
oh, I'm accidentally in the M section,
so halfway through the phone book.
But what do I now know
about John Harvard?
Is he to the left or to the right?
So he's obviously to the left,
because J comes before M. So what
I can do literally and
what your computer does
figuratively is tear the problem
in half, throw half of the problem
away, leaving us now with
the same fundamental problem,
but it's half as big.
So I've gone from a thousand
pages suddenly to 500 pages.
And compare this to the other two, 1,000
pages, 999, 998, versus 1,000 pages,
998, 996, 994.
That's still slow.
I went from 1,000 to 500 in
just one step of this algorithm.
What do I do next?
I go roughly to the middle here.
Oh, I went a little too far.
I'm in the E section now.
So is John Harvard to
the left or right now?
So he's to the right.
So I can again tear the problem
in half, throw the left half away,
knowing now that John Harvard
must alphabetically be in here.
And I can divide and divide and divide
and conquer this problem again and again
by using that heuristic of
going left or going right.
And I dare say, if I
do this correctly, I'll
eventually be left with one single page
on which John Harvard's number actually
is.
Or maybe he's not in
the phone book at all.
So how many steps maximally might
that third and final algorithm take?
It's not a thousand.
It's not even 500 or 501.
How many times can you divide a
thousand pages in half again and again
and again, roughly?
AUDIENCE: I want to say nine.
DAVID MALAN: So 9, 10.
So typically 10 times, give or take.
There's a bit of rounding there because
it's not a perfect power of two,
but roughly 10 times.
Like, that is fundamentally better
than both of the two algorithms
because I go from a thousand
pages to 500 to 250 to 125 and so
forth, literally halving
the problem again and again.
So we can actually appreciate and
see this even more so graphically.
And this is among the things
we'll do later in the term
when we speak to not only
writing correct code,
but is your code well designed?
Is it better than your previous code?
Is it better than someone else's code?
Is it better than some other product?
If you have given more thought to the
algorithms and the quality thereof,
you can perhaps minimize the
time required to solve problems
but no less correctly.
So if we have a simple xy plot
here, on the y-axis or vertical
is the amount of time to
solve in whatever unit
of measure, seconds, pages,
however you want to count.
On the horizontal or x-axis is
the size of the problem measured
in, for instance, numbers of pages.
So this would mean zero
pages in the phone book.
This would mean a lot of
This would mean no time to solve.
This would mean a lot of time to solve.
What's the relationship then,
among those three algorithms?
Well, the first one is essentially
a straight line, a slope of one.
And if the phone book
has n pages in it, we'll
describe the slope here as
essentially 1 over 1 for the algorithm
with the first algorithm,
turning page by page by page.
Which is to say, if we were to add one
more page to the phone book next year,
first algorithm is going
to take one more step.
But the second algorithm
is definitely better.
It's definitely faster, but
it's still a straight line.
So it's going to take roughly n over
2 steps on average, because you only
have to go through
half of the phone book
because you're going
two pages at a time,
instead of the whole phone
book in the worst case,
if someone's name is Z, to go
through every page in total.
So if we actually compare these--
let me just draw some dashed lines.
Suppose that you have this
many pages in the phone book.
If you just draw this
vertical white line here,
it's going to take this much time
in red using the first algorithm,
but it's going to literally
take half as much time
in yellow for the second
algorithm because you're literally
going two pages at once.
But the third and final algorithm
is a fundamentally different shape.
It instead looks a little
something like this.
It looks like it's flatter
and flatter and flatter.
It's always increasing.
It never gets perfectly flat.
But it grows so much more slowly
as a function of phone book size.
And for those who
recall their logarithms,
this would be described
as log base 2 of n.
And in fact, that's
where the math came from.
Log base 2 of 1,000 is
roughly 10 in total,
even if you need a calculator
to confirm as much.
But this shape is
fundamentally different.
Why?
Well, suppose that Cambridge,
where we are, and Allston,
the town across the street next
year, combine their two phone books.
And they go from a thousand pages each
to one phone book with 2,000 pages.
The first algorithm is going
to literally take twice
as many steps or pages.
Second algorithm is going to
take half as many or 50% more
because you're going two at a time.
But the third algorithm is
going to barely miss a beat.
Why?
Because if this is a thousand pages
here and 2,000 pages is over there,
just inferring from the
shape of the green line,
it's not going to be much higher on the
vertical axis than the other two were.
So more specifically, if you have
a 2,000 page phone book next year,
how many more steps will it take you
using that third and final algorithm?
Just one, because you'll divide
and conquer a 2,000 page phone book
into a 1,000 page phone book, and then
you're back at the original story.
And that's the sort of power
of learning algorithms.
That's the power of learning computer
science and learning how to program
is to be able to navigate
big data, so to speak.
Things the size of google, things the
size of artificial intelligence training
data sets using better
and better, more clever
algorithms that perform
faster, and therefore
not only make the
software more competitive,
but also make it more usable and more
favorable for people like you and me
when using that software.
So when it comes to implementing
algorithms as programmers,
as computer scientists, what you're
really doing is taking these algorithms,
which might be expressed in English
conceptually as we just did,
but really just
translating them to code,
be it C or C++ or Python or R or Ruby or
any number of other languages that exist
in the world.
But for now, let's consider
how we might implement
that algorithm using something that's
literally still English, but pseudocode.
Something that is still
correct, but precise and finite,
as per Professor
Kernighan's advice, which
is to say use your own
vernacular of English and just
say what you mean but very succinctly.
There's no one way to write pseudocode.
It's not some formal language.
I'm just going to convert the
steps I did intuitively to step
by step instructions as follows.
Step one, what I did was pretty
much pick up the phone book.
Step two, what I did was pretty
much open to middle of phone book
for the third algorithm.
Step three, look at page.
Step four, if person is on page,
then, step five, call person.
If that does not prove
to be the case, step six,
else if the person is
earlier in the book, then
open to the middle of the left half of
the book and then go back to line three.
Then, else if the person
is later in the book,
open to the middle of the right half of
the book and, again, go to line three.
Else, there's a fourth and final case.
If the person like John Harvard is
not on the page, is not earlier,
is not later, what's the fourth
scenario we'd best consider?
He's just not there.
Else we should do something
specific like quit.
Now, as an aside, everyone
in this room has probably
had one of these stupid
technical support issues
where your phone or your
laptop or your desktop computer
just freeze all of a sudden, or maybe
it spontaneously reboots for no reason.
Odds are that's because not you but
some other human made a mistake.
They probably wrote code
working at Microsoft or Apple
or Google or somewhere else,
and they didn't actually
anticipate that, oh, there
could be a fourth scenario that
could happen in the real world.
But if there's no code that
tells the computer what
to do in that fourth
and final scenario, who
knows what the computer is going to do?
It might, by default, reboot.
It might, by default, freeze.
That's just a hint of the bugs,
the mistakes in software to come.
But even though this is just
one way to write this code,
a.k.a. pseudocode, there are
some salient characteristics
that we'll use throughout today.
One, there are these
verbs, these actions.
And henceforth, as aspiring
computer scientists or programmers,
we're going to start to call these by
what a more and more technical audience
would.
These are functions.
A function is an action or a verb.
It's like a bite-sized task
that a computer can do for you.
Those then are functions
in this here pseudocode.
But there's other types of code in here.
There are these things here.
If else if else if else.
Those are examples of what we're
going to start calling conditionals.
These are sort of proverbial forks in
the road where maybe you go this way,
maybe you go this way, but you decide
which way to go based on a question.
The questions that you ask
are what we'll technically
call Boolean expressions named
after mathematician Boole.
A Boolean expression is a
question with a yes or no answer,
a true or false answer, a black or
white answer, a one or zero answer.
There's two possibilities, and there's
a hint of the binary underneath.
A Boolean expression is going
to tell you yes or no, you
should go down that fork in the road.
Notice what's important here is that
indentation mattered as a result.
Notice that on line four when I first
asked if the person is on page question
mark, so to speak, I should only
do line five per its indentation
if the answer is yes
or true, I should only
open to the middle of the left half
of the book and go back to line three
if person is instead
earlier in the book.
So indentation in pseudocode and
in many programming languages
has logical significance.
It tells you whether
to do things or not.
But there's another construct in here.
Go back to.
Go back to, which literally makes me
go back to line three, potentially
again and again and again,
creating some kind of cycle
or what we'll typically
call a loop instead.
So even in this relatively
simple real world algorithm,
we have these four fundamental
characteristics of most computer
programs that we will
write in this class,
and you might write beyond this class,
that we have some technical jargon now
to describe them.
But what's important to note
is that line 8 and line 11,
even though they're saying go back
to line three, go back to line three,
you might think you're
running the risk of what
we'll call an infinite loop where
you literally get stuck in a loop
forever, which doesn't sound like
a good thing if, at some point,
you want to turn your computer off,
even though it's still working.
But these will not
induce infinite loops.
Why?
What is happening in this particular
algorithm every time we go back to line
three that guarantees eventually we
will stop going back to line three?
AUDIENCE: The person is
on the page, you call it.
DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
If the person is on the page, we
will call them or we will quit.
But more importantly, because we keep
dividing and conquering the problem,
in this case, having the phone
book, having the phone book,
eventually we're going to run out of
phone book, in which case, indeed,
John Harvard is either on that
page or not And we will call
or we will quit instead.
So we'll see in time.
And in fact, allow me to promise.
Odds are at some point
you will write code
that seems to take control
over the computer for you,
where it's doing something,
doing something, doing something,
and it literally won't
respond to you anymore.
That's just going to be because
of a mistake, a so-called bug
that you yourself will invariably
have added to your code accidentally.
But we'll show you ways for terminating
it or breaking out of those conditions.
And indeed, what we'll
do in just a little bit
after a break for today's lecture
is explore not just these concepts,
but some of the ways you can
use them to solve real and very
visual and audio problems.
But for now, let's at least
connect it to something
that's been all too germane in recent
months, the past few years, namely
artificial intelligence, which
is a topic we'll come back to
at the end of the
course, too, to give you
a sense of what the connection
is with what everyone's
been talking about in
the world of AI and what
it is we're going to spend the next few
weeks building up to by writing code.
If you were to try to implement
something like a chat bot,
for instance, that just
answers questions and has
a conversation with you, you
could do that using pseudocode,
and as we'll soon see, you can use C,
Python, any number of other languages
too.
That pseudocode might look like
this when implementing a chat bot.
You could tell the chat bot, if
the student says hello to you,
then say hello back.
And the indentation, as per earlier,
implies this is conditional.
Else if the student says goodbye
to you, say goodbye to the student.
Else if the student asks you
how you are, say you are well.
So you can just enumerate question
after question after question
and just handle all of these
conditional possibilities.
But things kind of escalate
quickly, especially
with the tools of today like ChatGPT.
Are we really going to have
the wherewithal as programmers
to write another conditional like else
if the student asks why 111 in binary
is 7 in decimal-- like,
this kind of hints at,
oh my God, there's an
infinite number of things
this human could ask the chat bot.
Do we really have to write an
infinite number of conditionals?
That's just not possible.
Like, there's not
enough time in the day,
there's not enough
lines of code available.
Artificial intelligence surely needs
to be able to figure some of this
out instead.
And so indeed, this is
not how you implement AI,
but rather how you implement
an AI like a chat bot
is you typically train it
based on lots and lots of data.
You give it lots of inputs,
lots of inputs, training data,
and let it figure out what it should
say in response to certain questions.
And it boils down to
a lot of probability,
a lot of statistics, otherwise
known now as large language models,
which, if we really peek under the
hood, are actually typically implemented
with what are called neural networks
inspired by the world of biology,
whereby we humans have
all of these neurons that
transmit electrical signals such
that my brain tells my hand to move
this way, this way, and this other way.
And so what computer
scientists have been doing over
the past many years is implementing
in software using literally zeros
and ones, graphs or networks,
neural networks, that
look a little something like this, where
each of the circles represents a neuron,
each of the arrows represents
a pathway between them,
and provides as input to
these networks huge amounts
of data like all of the internet,
all of Wikipedia, all of the books
that it might consume as input.
And then the goal of this neural
network, as per this single final neuron
right here, is to produce
an answer to a question.
Maybe it's simple like, yes, no, or
maybe it's something like the answer
to the 111 question or how are you
or goodbye or hello or the like.
And what these neural networks do
is use statistics and probability
and try to output the most
probabilistically likely answer
to this question that's been asked and
really just hope that it is correct.
There is no programmer
at OpenAI or Google
or Microsoft that's trying to
anticipate every one of these questions
we might ask, not only in English
but in other languages as well.
So you might be wondering why there's
this 8 foot duck on the stage.
So the persona that CS50's own AI
takes is in fact that of a rubber duck,
because it turns out in
programming circles--
and this is true long before CS50--
it has often been recommended to
students and aspiring programmers
that you keep literally a
physical rubber duck on your desk.
The idea being, in the absence of
a friend, family member, colleague,
TA who could answer technical
questions for you, if you're alone
in your room in Mather at night, you
can talk to the duck, maybe door closed,
and ask the duck your
questions, or, more importantly,
talk the duck through what
confusion you're having.
And the mere act of talking
through the problem,
explaining logically what you're trying
to do, what you're actually doing,
and what the error
actually is, invariably,
that sort of proverbial light bulb goes
off and you realize, oh, I'm an idiot.
I hear in my own words
where I've gone awry.
And even though this duck will never
say anything back to you, that alone,
rubber duck debugging or rubber ducking,
tends to be a valuable programming
technique, believe it or not.
But thanks to these
large language models,
we have not only physical
but virtual ducks as well.
And so available to you will be in
this class not tools like ChatGPT
and the like, which are,
through policy, disallowed.
It is not reasonable to
use ChatGPT and the like.
But you are allowed and encouraged
to use CS50's own AI based
tools, which resemble those same
tools but know something about CS50
and aspire to behave akin to a
good teaching fellow guiding you
to solutions as opposed to
handing you something outright.
So this is a tool that will
be available at literally
this URL throughout the course.
CS50.ai.
It will also be embedded in the
programming environment you'll soon
meet, which is called Visual Studio
Code, a cloud based version thereof.
The duck will live in that environment
as well, as well as on stage from time
to time, which is to say we'll
not only talk about, but use
throughout the course
this thing known as AI.
But this is ultimately code that we're
going to start writing next week.
And unfortunately, this
code here is written
in a language called C. This is
essentially the program that I lost
two points on some 25 plus years ago.
It does look admittedly cryptic.
That's why today what we'll focus
on is not what this code looks like,
nor the zeros and ones that that code
gets converted to so your computer
can understand as input
what you want it to do.
We're going to focus on a much
more visual incarnation of this.
But I know thus far this has been a lot.
So let's go ahead and take
a five minute break here,
and when we come back in five,
we'll do some actual programming.
So see you in five.
All right.
So it's now time to solve with
actual code some actual problems,
albeit in a fun and
visual and audio way.
But recall that where
we left off was this.
Starting next week, you'll be writing
code that ultimately looks like this,
but thankfully, you will not
be writing zeros and ones,
and no normal person,
myself included, can
understand what all of these
zeros and ones are at a glance.
We could take out some
paper, pencil, and probably
figure it out very tediously.
But this is exactly the point.
Computers only understand this
stuff, but what we as programmers
will start writing today and
beyond is code at a higher level.
And indeed, this is going to be--
this is going to be frequent
within computer science
where there's different levels of
abstraction that we operate at.
And the lowest level, the nittiest
gritty, is like the zeros and ones
that computer understand.
That's it in this class
for zeros and ones.
Hopefully you at least
have wrapped your mind
around why zeros and ones
can be used in triples
and as bytes to represent
higher and higher numbers.
But let's just now agree
that computers can do that.
Let's abstract away from
that detail and focus
on higher level languages than zeros
and ones, namely a language like this.
So this is an example of
the very first programming
language I learned back in the day as
per that homework in a language called
C.
It's an older language, but it remains
one of the most popular languages
in omnipresent languages nowadays
because it's incredibly fast
and it's particularly good at
making devices operate quickly.
For us pedagogically,
the value of C is not
that you're probably in Silicon
Valley and other such jobs
going to be using C yourself
that much, but because it's
going to provide a conceptual
foundation on top of which we introduce
other languages, like Python, which
is newer and improved, so to speak,
that gives you more and more
functionality for free out of the box
by abstracting away some of the stuff
we'll focus on in the coming days first.
So at the end of the
day, you should better
understand languages like
Python and JavaScript
and SQL because of your underlying
understanding of a language like C.
But this is too much for the first day.
Many of you will think that this
is too much for the second week.
But in fact, C is really
only sort of scary
looking because all of this darn
punctuation and syntax, the semicolon,
the parentheses, the double quotes,
the curly braces, and the like.
And I concur.
This is intellectually uninteresting,
and a lot of the challenges early
on when learning programming is you
just don't have the muscle memory
that I or some of the teaching
fellows might for knowing
what symbol should be where.
But that's going to come with
time and practice, I guarantee it.
What we'll do for today,
though, is just throw away
all of that intellectually uninteresting
detail and focus really on ideas.
And some of you might
be in your comfort zone
here because if back
in middle school you
were playing with a programming
language called Scratch,
you were probably using at the time just
to have fun in class or out of class,
making games, animations,
interactive art.
What you probably didn't use it
for, at least in middle school,
was to consider and explore
programming languages themselves.
But what's wonderful about Scratch,
which is this graphical programming
language from down the street at MIT,
where it was invented some years ago,
is you can program not by
using your keyboard per se,
but by dragging and dropping puzzle
pieces, otherwise known as blocks,
that will snap together if it
makes logical sense to do so.
And what you won't have to deal with
is parentheses and double quotes
and semicolons and all of
that, at least until next week.
But the nice thing about
Scratch is that after this week
and after the so-called
problem set zero,
the first assignment in
which you'll use Scratch,
you'll have a mental model via
which it will be easier to pick up
all of the subsequent syntax as well.
So let's see how we can
start programming in Scratch
by making the simplest
of programs first.
You can do this at scratch.mit.edu.
You needn't do this now in the moment.
Problem set zero will walk you
through all of these steps.
But what I've done here is opened
up at scratch.mit.edu, precisely
the default web page therein.
This is after having
clicked the Create button
in Scratch, which is going to allow
me to create my first program.
But first, a tour of
the user interface here,
and what is ultimately available to you.
Well, within the Scratch
environment, we'll
see a few different
regions of the screen.
One, we have this palette
of puzzle pieces at left.
The blue ones relate to motion,
the purple ones relate to looks,
the pink ones relate
to sound, and so forth.
So the color of the blocks
just roughly categorizes
what that block's purpose in life is.
We're going to be able to use those
puzzle pieces by dragging and dropping
them from left to right.
In the right here, in
the middle of the screen
is where I'm going to
write my actual programs.
This is where I'll drag and
drop these puzzle pieces,
lock them together, and
actually write my code.
What am I going to be coding?
Well, I'm going to be
controlling one or more sprites.
Much like in the world of games are
familiar, a sprite is like a character
that you might see on the screen.
The default character
in the world of Scratch
is, in fact, a cat that looks like this.
And if in this case,
I have just one cat,
I can then make that cat do things
in his own little world at top right
by making the cat move
up, down, left, right,
spinning around, or doing
other things as well.
But if you want to
introduce a dog or a bird
or any number of other custom
characters, you just add more sprites
and they get their own
place in that same world.
As for how to think about
movement in this world,
it's actually pretty
familiar, even though it
gets a little numeric for a moment.
If Scratch at the moment is in the
middle of the screen, the cat is at 0, 0
if you think about x, y-coordinates
or latitude longitude.
If you move the cat all the way
up, this would still be x equals 0,
but it would be y 180.
What's the 180?
180 pixels vertically
or dots on the screen.
This is negative 180 pixels
on the screen at the bottom.
By contrast, if you go left and
right, your x value might change.
Negative 240, but y is 0, or
positive 240 and y is 0 as well.
But most of the time you won't
need to know or care about what
the pixel coordinates of the cat are.
All you're generally going to care
about is the programmer, most likely,
is do you want the cat to go
relatively up, down, left, or right,
and let MIT figure out the mathematics
of moving this thing around
in most cases.
All right.
So let's go ahead and introduce
the first of these programs
by doing something quite simple, as we
did in C there, but a little more simply
by writing code as follows.
I'm going to go back to scratch.mit.edu.
I've already clicked, per
before, the Create button.
And if I click on the yellow
category of blocks here at left--
and I'll zoom in-- we'll see a
whole bunch of yellow puzzle pieces.
And probably the most
common one you will
use to write code in Scratch for
just this first week is literally
when green flag clicked.
Why?
Well, if we go back over to
the cat's world at top right,
notice that above the
cat's rectangular world,
there's not only a
green flag for starting,
there's a red stop sign
for stopping as well.
So let's do this.
Let me go ahead and click and drag.
When green flag clicked anywhere
into the middle and let go.
And now I'm going to go
to looks, and it looks
like there's a whole bunch
of purple puzzle pieces here.
I'm going to choose something
simple like say hello, drag it.
And notice if I get
just close enough, it's
going to want to
magnetically snap together.
So I'll just do that
and it does its thing.
The fact that there's
this white oval with text
means that is an input to
this, say, puzzle piece.
I can literally then
change what the input
is if I want to more
conventionally say hello, world.
Which in fact, according to lore, was
the very first program written in C,
and nowadays in most every language,
including in Brian Kernighan's book.
So hello world is
generally the first program
that most any programmer first writes.
So that's it as programs go.
Let me go ahead and zoom out here.
Let me go over to the right and click
the green flag, and somewhat excitingly,
maybe underwhelmingly, we've now
written a program that quite simply says
hello world on the screen.
Now let's make this a little
more technical for just a moment.
What is this here puzzle
piece, as I keep calling it?
It's actually a similar--
it's an incarnation one of the
ideas from our pseudocode before.
What did we call those actions and
verbs last time in my pseudocode?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID MALAN: Functions.
That's right.
So these purple puzzle pieces
here are indeed functions,
and some functions, as we can see,
take inputs, like hello comma world.
After all, how does
Scratch know what to say?
You have to provide the
cat with input, which
is to say functions can
indeed take inputs like this.
In this case one input,
but we'll see opportunities
for passing in more input as well.
What the cat is doing though, visually
on the screen here at top right,
is what's generally
called a side effect.
Sometimes when you call a function,
it does something visually.
And in this case, you're seeing
literally a cartoon speech
bubble, hello world.
That is the side effect
of this function.
So if we now want to map this to
our world of inputs and outputs
and see where this side effect
is, this is the paradigm
I proposed at the start of class that
is computer science in a nutshell
and will be the framework
we use literally
throughout the class, no matter how--
no matter how the languages
in particular evolve.
So what's the input to
this particular program?
Well, this white oval,
hello world is my input.
The algorithm, step by step
instructions for solving some problem,
is implemented in code,
this language called Scratch
by way of this purple puzzle piece.
And the output of that
function, given this input,
is the side effect whereby the cat
indeed says hello world visually
on the screen in that speech bubble.
So the exact same paradigm
with which we began today
governs how exactly this cat here works.
Well, let's actually
go back to this program
and make it a little more
interesting than that.
Let me go ahead and
click the red stop sign.
And let me actually use a different type
of puzzle piece, another function that
does something a little different.
First, I'm going to get
rid of the say block.
So I'm going to not
only pull it away, I'm
going to drag it over anywhere
at left and just let go
and it will delete itself automatically.
Or I could right click or Control
click, and from a little menu
I could also explicitly say delete.
And what I'm going to
do now is under sensing,
which is a light blue shade of puzzle
piece-- there's a whole bunch here,
but I'm going to focus on this one.
Ask something and wait.
And the default text
is, what's your name?
And that's fine.
But because it's a
white oval, that input
can be manually changed by me if
I wanted to change the question.
I'm going to drag it over here.
It's going to magnetically
snap together.
And I'm OK with that question.
But what do I want to
say with the answer?
Well, let's go ahead and do this.
I could go to looks again.
I could grab another say
block, let it snap in,
and I could say something
like, hello, David.
But this is going to be the
first of many bugs that I make,
intentionally or otherwise.
Let me click the green flag.
Scratch is now, just like in a web
browser, prompting me for some input
here.
So let me go ahead and type in my name.
David.
Enter.
And voila.
It works.
Hello, David.
I'm kind of cheating, though, right?
Because if I zoom out,
stop, and play again.
Let me type in Julia's name here,
enter, and it still says hello, David.
So that didn't really implement
the idea that I wanted.
All right, so how can I fix this?
Well, it seems that this time
I want more than a side effect.
I want to use the value
that the human types in.
And for this, we need
another feature of functions,
which is that not only can they
sometimes have side effects,
something visually happens.
Some functions can hand you back
a value, a so-called return value,
that will allow you to actually
reuse whatever the human typed in.
So a return value is something that
gets virtually handed back to you
and you can store it in something
called a variable, like x, y, and z
in mathematics, and you can
generally reuse it one or more times.
So let me actually
draw our attention then
to, at left, not only the blue puzzle
piece, ask what's your name and wait,
but notice that there's a
special puzzle piece below it,
this blue oval called answer, and
that represents what a computer
scientist would call a return value.
So MIT has kind of bundled
it together side by side
to make clear that one of those
pieces relates to the other.
What it means is that I can do this.
I can drag this oval and use this oval
as the input to the save function.
Now, notice it's not the same size, but
it is the right shape, so that's OK.
Scratch will grow or shrink
things to fit properly.
But this too isn't quite right.
Let me go ahead and do this.
Let me go ahead and stop
that, click the green flag.
I'll type in my name again.
D-A-V-I-D. Enter.
And it's just kind of weird or rude.
Like, I wanted a hello at least, and
it just said David on the screen.
OK, so I can fix that.
Let me stop with the red stop sign.
Let me just separate these temporarily.
And I can leave it in the
middle there, but they
have no logical connection temporarily.
Let me go back up to looks.
Let me grab a say block, a
second one, and let me go ahead
and say, just to be
grammatical, hello, space.
And then I'll reconnect this here.
So at the moment it looks like
what I want, I want a hello, comma,
and then the return value printed out
based on whatever the human typed in.
So let me zoom out.
Let me click the green flag.
Again, what's your name?
D-A-V-I-D. And watch
the cat's side effect.
Enter.
It's still not greeting me properly.
There's no hello.
And if in case it was too
fast, let's do it again.
Green flag.
D-A-V-I-D. Enter.
It rudely just says my
name, which is weird.
What's the bug here, though?
It's a little more subtle.
Why?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: It's just quickly going.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
It's just too quickly going over
the say command or the say function,
in this case.
My Mac, your PC, your phone,
it's just so darn fast.
Both are happening, but too fast
for my human eyes to even notice.
So we can solve this
in a number of ways.
I could actually use a different
puzzle piece altogether.
In fact, MIT kind of anticipated this.
Notice the first puzzle
piece in purple is say hello
for a specific number
of seconds, and you
can specify not just the
message, but the number
of seconds, ergo two inputs, otherwise
now known as arguments to a function.
An input to a function
is just an argument now.
And that would be a fix here.
I could maybe a little
more explicitly do this.
I could go under events, scroll
down a little bit, and-- sorry,
under control in orange,
I could grab a wait block
and I could kind insert
it in the middle.
And this might actually help.
So I could click on the green flag.
D-A-V-I-D. Enter.
Hello, David.
And I could change the timing
to be a little more natural.
But what if I want the cat to
just say hello, David all in one
breath, so to speak.
Well, for that I'm going to need to
use a slightly different technique as
follows.
Let me go ahead and get rid of the wait.
Let me get rid of the second say block
and stop the cat with the stop sign.
Let me go under operators here and
let me somewhat cleverly grab this.
A join block at the bottom.
By default, it's using apple
and banana as placeholders,
but those are white ovals
so I can change those.
Let me drag this over the white
oval for the save function and let
go, and it will snap to fill.
Let me go ahead here and type hello,
comma, space instead of apple.
And what should I do instead of banana?
AUDIENCE: Answer.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
So it'd be answer return value--
the return value.
So let me go under sensing again.
Let me just drag another copy of it.
And you can use these
again and again and again.
They don't disappear.
I want to drag answer over banana
so that the second input to join
is actually, if you will, the
output of the ask block, like that.
And it snaps to fit.
So now if I go ahead and click
the green flag once more.
D-A-V-I-D. Enter.
Now we have the behavior
aesthetically that I cared about.
But beyond the aesthetics
of this, the goal here
really was to map it to, again, this
same paradigm, which we'll see here.
The algorithm and the output and the
input for this example are as follows.
The input to the say block was,
quote, unquote, what's your name?
The function, of course,
implementing that algorithm in code
was the ask and wait block.
The output, though, of the ask block
recalls not some visual side effect.
It is a return value called
answer, like a variable,
a special variable like
x, y, and z in math.
But in this one, we
generally in programming
describe variables with actual
words, not just letters.
But this output of the say block,
I kind of want to make room for it
to pass it into the say
block as a second argument.
So let's do this.
Let's take one step back and
propose that now for the join
block that I just used.
It takes two inputs
hello, space and answer.
The function in question
is indeed the join block.
The output of this had
better be hello, David.
What do I want to do with
the output of the join block?
Well, let me clear the screen.
Let me move this over, because
now the output of the join block
is going to instantly become
the input to the say block
so that the output now
in this multistep process
is the side effect of hello, David.
So the fact that I nested these
blocks on top of one another
was very much deliberate.
If I zoom in here, notice that hello
and answer are on top of join, join
is on top of the say block.
And if you think back
to high school math,
this is like when you
had parentheses and you
had to do the things inside parentheses
before the things outside parentheses.
It's the same idea, but I'm just
visually stacking them instead.
But outputs can become inputs depending
on what the function there expects.
Let me pause here and see
if there's any questions
about not so much what the cat is
doing, but how the cat is doing this.
Questions at hand?
All right.
Well, let's make the cat
more cat-like and do this.
Let me throw away all the say
block and just let go there.
And let me introduce at bottom
left a nice feature of scratch
whereby there's also
these extensions that
tend to use the cloud, the internet,
to give you even more functionality.
And in fact, I'm going to click on
this extension up here, text to speech.
And if I click on that, I
suddenly get a whole new category
of blocks at the bottom.
Text to speech.
They happen to be green.
But what's nice here is
that I can actually now
have the cat say something audibly.
So let me drag the speak block
here instead of the say block.
I don't want it to just say hello.
Let me stop that.
So let me go back under operators.
Let me grab another join block,
because I threw the other one away.
Let me change apple
to hello, space again.
Let me go to sensing.
Let me drag answer to banana again.
And now let me hit the green flag and
let me type in my name, D-A-V-I-D.
And in a moment I'll hit enter and.
COMPUTER: Hello, David.
DAVID MALAN: All right.
It's not exactly cat-like,
but it was synthesized.
But it turns out under these text to
speech blocks, there are some others.
Set voice to alto, for instance,
seems to be the default.
But let's change this.
So notice that some puzzle pieces
don't just take white ovals.
They might even have drop downs.
So whoever created that
puzzle piece decided
in advance what the available choices
are for that input per the dropdown.
So I'm going to change it
to squeak, which sounds--
or actually kitten sounds even more apt.
Let me zoom out, click the
green flag, type my name.
D-A-V-I-D. Enter.
COMPUTER: Meow, meow.
DAVID MALAN: That's interesting.
So it doesn't seem to
matter what I type.
So how about David Malan.
COMPUTER: Meow, meow, meow.
DAVID MALAN: So it seems to
meow proportional to how long
the phrase is that I typed in.
It can get a little creepy quickly.
If I change kitten to giant.
Let me go ahead and hit Play.
D-A-V-I-D. Enter.
COMPUTER: Hello, David.
DAVID MALAN: So you can,
for very non-academic ways,
start to have fun with this,
but just playing around
with these various inputs and outputs.
But let's actually make the cat do
something more cat-like and indeed meow
instead of saying any words at all.
So let me throw all of that away.
Let me go now under sound.
Let me drag the play sound until done.
And notice in the dropdown here, by
default, you just get the cat sound.
You can record your own sounds.
There's a whole library
of dogs and birds
and all sorts of sounds you
can import into the program.
I'll keep it simple with cat.
And let me click the green flag.
COMPUTER: Meow.
DAVID MALAN: All right.
So the cat meowed once.
If I want the cat to meow
again, I could do this.
COMPUTER: Meow.
DAVID MALAN: If I want the cat to meow
a third time, I could again hit play.
COMPUTER: Meow.
DAVID MALAN: So this is kind of
tedious if to play this game,
I have to keep clicking the
button, keep clicking the button
to keep the cat alive
virtually in this way.
So maybe I want this to happen
again and again and again.
Well, let me just do that.
Let me sort of drag and drop.
Or I could right click
or Control click and then
a little menu would let me
Copy-Paste or duplicate blocks.
But I'll just keep
dragging and dropping.
Let's do this.
COMPUTER: Meow.
Meow.
DAVID MALAN: Cat's kind
of hungry, unhappy.
So let's slow things down
so it's adorable again.
So let me go under control.
Let me grab one of those wait one
second, and I'll plop this here.
Another one.
Let me plop it here.
Click play again.
COMPUTER: Meow.
Meow.
DAVID MALAN: Cuter.
Less hungry.
Sure.
But this program is
now, I daresay, correct
if my goal is to get the
cat's meow three times.
But now, even if you've never programmed
before, critique this program.
It is not well-designed,
even though it is correct.
In other words, it could be better.
How, might you think?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: A loop.
DAVID MALAN: So using a loop.
And why?
Why are you encouraging me to use
a loop even though it works as is?
AUDIENCE: It's easier to plot.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
So to summarize, it's
just easier to use a loop
because I could specify explicitly
in one place how many times I want it
to loop.
And moreover, frankly, any time you are
copying and pasting something in code
or dragging the same thing
again and again, odds are you're
doing something foolish.
Why?
Because you're repeating
yourself unnecessarily.
And this is a bit extreme,
but suppose I want
to change this program later so that the
cat pauses two seconds in between meows.
Well, obviously I can just
go in here and do two.
But what if I forget?
And suppose this program isn't,
like, five or six puzzle pieces.
Suppose it's 50 or 60 or 500 or 600.
Eventually I or a colleague I'm
working with is going to screw up.
They're going to change a value in one
place, forget to change it in another.
So why are you inviting the
probability of making a mistake?
Just simplify things so that you only
have to change inputs in one place.
So how can I do this?
Let me zoom out.
Let me throw most of
this duplication away,
leaving me with just the
play and the wait function.
Let me now, under control
as well, grab one of these.
I could, for instance,
repeat as follows.
Let me grab a repeat.
I'm going to have to
move these in two parts.
So I'm going to move this down.
It's too small, but it will
grow to fit the right shape.
Then let me reattach it up here.
Let me change the default 10 to a 3.
And now I think I've done exactly what
you were encouraging, which is simplify.
And I click play now.
COMPUTER: Meow.
Meow.
DAVID MALAN: Now and.
COMPUTER: Meow.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
So still correct, but arguably
better designed as a result.
I can keep things simple and
change things now in just one place
and it will continue to work.
But this is getting a
little tedious now, I claim.
Like, why am I implementing
the idea of meowing?
Wouldn't MIT have been better
to have just implemented
a meow puzzle piece for us?
Because the whole thing
is themed around a cat.
Why is there not a meow puzzle piece?
Why do I need to go through all of this
complexity to build that functionality?
Well, what's nice about
Scratch and what's
nice about programming
languages in general
is you can generally invent your own
puzzle pieces, your own functions,
and then use and reuse them.
So let me go ahead and do this.
I'm going to go under my
blocks in pink down here.
I'm going to go ahead
and click make a block,
and I'm going to be prompted
with this interface here.
And I'm going to call this block
literally meow, because apparently MIT
forgot to implement it for us.
And I'm just going to go ahead
and immediately click OK.
And what you'll see now is two things.
One, on the screen, I've been
given this placeholder pink piece
that says define meow as follows.
So anything I attach to the
bottom of that define block
is going to define the
meaning of meowing.
And at top left, notice
what I have under my blocks.
I now have a pink
puzzle piece called meow
that is a new function that will do
whatever that other block of code
tells the cat to do.
So what do I want to do here?
Well, I'm going to
keep it simple for now.
I'm going to move the play sound
meow until done and wait two seconds.
Though let's change it back to
one second to move things along.
And now let me drag
the meow puzzle piece
over to my loop such that
now, what's it going to do?
It's going to meow three times.
And just to be dramatic,
out of sight, out of mind.
Let me, for no technical
reason, just drag
this all the way to the bottom
of the screen and then scroll
back up just to make the point
visually that now meowing exists.
That is an implementation detail
that we can abstract away,
not caring how it exists, because I
now know at a higher conceptual level,
if I want a meow, I just use the meow
puzzle piece, and I or someone else
dealt with already how
to implement meowing.
So now let me go ahead and hit play.
COMPUTER: Meow.
Meow.
DAVID MALAN: OK, so same exact
code, but arguably better
design because I've now given
myself reusable code so I don't have
to Copy-Paste those several blocks.
I can just use meow again and again.
But let's make one refinement.
Let me actually scroll down to
where I did in fact implement this.
Let me Control click
or right click on it
and let me edit the pink
block that I created
a moment ago, because I want to practice
what I've been preaching about inputs.
So I don't want this function
just to be called meow.
I want this function
to also take an input,
and just for consistency with our use
of n earlier, which in computer science
generally means number,
let me meow n times.
And just so that this puzzle piece
is even more programmer friendly,
let me add just a textual label
that has no technical significance
other than to make this
function read left to right
in a more English friendly way.
Meow n times.
Let me click OK.
And now notice this thing at
the bottom has changed such
that it's not only called meow,
there's explicit mention of n,
which is a circle, which is exactly
the variable shape that we saw earlier
when it was called answer.
This is not a return value, though.
This is what, again, we're going to call
an argument, an input to a function.
So let me do this.
I'm going to move this
back up to the top
so I can see everything
in one place, and I'm
going to make one modification,
because my goal now
is to make a new and improved version of
meowing that actually takes into account
how many times I want the cat to meow.
So instead of using a loop in my own
program under when green flag clicked,
I'm going to detach this temporarily.
I'm going to move this away.
I'm going to move this code over here,
and I'm going to reattach it here.
So focusing for the
moment on just the left,
meow is now defined as repeating three
times the following two functions.
Play sound and wait.
But that's not quite right.
I want to get rid of the three.
So what can I do?
Because I created this input to the
meow function myself a moment ago,
I can actually drag a
copy of it over right
that is change the three
to be generally an n.
So now I have a function called meow
that will meow any number of times.
And what's nice now is my actual program
that is governed by that green flag,
I can type in three, I can type in 10, I
can type in 100, and it will just work.
And henceforth, I can,
again, dramatically
scroll this down so we don't
know or care about it anymore.
Now my program is a single line
whereby this notion of meowing
has been abstracted away by just
defining my own function or custom
block.
Questions, then, about just
this idea, this principle
of creating your own functions to hide
implementation details once you've
solved a problem?
Therefore, you don't want to have
to think about that same problem
ever again.
And that's the beauty of
programming, typically.
Questions on what here we just did?
No?
All right.
Well, let's do this.
Let's now make this a little
more interactive in code.
Let me go to this green flag.
Let me scroll down and just
throw all of this hard work
away that we have copies on the courses
website of all of these programs step
by step if you want to
review them in slower detail.
Let's do this.
Under control, turns out
there's other ways to loop.
There's this forever block that
will just do something forever.
So in the forever block, there's
some place for some other code.
And I'm going to move
to the control section
here and grab one of these if
blocks, so one of these conditionals.
Let's plug that in here.
And now notice if, and then there's
this sort of trapezoid-like placeholder
that's going to probably fit what?
The if is a conditional.
Forever is a loop.
Say and so forth have been functions.
What was the other key term we used?
So a Boolean expression.
We need to put one of those yes,
no or true, false questions here.
So what are those?
Well, I've been using
Scratch for some years,
so I under sensing there's
one of these shapes here.
Touching mouse pointer, question mark.
The question mark literally evokes
the whole idea of a Boolean expression
being yes, no.
It's way too big to fit,
but it is the right shape.
So let me drag it.
Let go.
It's going to grow to fill.
And now let me go to sound.
Let me grab that play
sound, meow until done,
and put it inside that conditional
such that what kind of program
have I just implemented here, arguably?
What will this program do
when I click the green flag?
Well, nothing at the moment.
AUDIENCE: Not touching the cat.
DAVID MALAN: But I'm
not touching the cat.
So if I move the mouse
pointer to the cat.
COMPUTER: Meow.
DAVID MALAN: Again.
DAVID MALAN: It's kind of implementing
the idea of petting a cat, if you will,
because I'm forever just
waiting and waiting and waiting.
Is the mouse pointer touching
that sprite, touching that cat?
And only if so, go ahead and
play that sound meow until done.
But now we can make things
a little more interesting.
Let me stop this and let me do
something actually completely different.
Let me throw all this hard work away.
Let me go under extensions.
Let me go to video sensing, because
lots of laptops, my own included,
has a little webcam nowadays.
Let me approve use of that there.
And you can see me in the frame.
And let me do this.
Let me drag one of these when
motion exceeds some measure.
And through trial and error, I figured
out that 50 tends to work well.
Let me step out of frame here
and program off to the side.
And if I go to play
sound meow until done,
notice that this is an alternative
to using when green flag clicked.
This is a category of
block that's constantly
waiting for what we'll call an event.
An event is just something that can
happen on the screen, a click, a drag,
a mouse movement, and so forth.
So let me zoom out here.
And now, if I can do this-- here we go.
No, too slow.
Still too slow.
Wait, did I click play?
Let's see.
Try again.
COMPUTER: Meow.
DAVID MALAN: There we go.
OK.
50 is a little too high, apparently.
So let's make this a little gentler.
10.
COMPUTER: Meow.
DAVID MALAN: OK, well.
DAVID MALAN: There we go.
COMPUTER: Meow.
DAVID MALAN: OK, so we've implemented
now more physically the idea of actually
responding to petting a cat.
COMPUTER: Meow.
Meow.
DAVID MALAN: Oh, damn it.
OK.
COMPUTER: Meow.
Meow.
DAVID MALAN: All right.
So this is a bug.
Like now-- this is MIT's fault.
So it's not stopping in response
to the red stop sign.
So what do you do in doubt?
Most extreme, you reboot.
For now, I'm just going
to close the window.
OK.
So now we've seen all
of those primitives
that we saw in that pseudocode, but
incarnated in this graphical programming
language, and again, without parentheses
and semicolons and double quotes and all
that punctuation that we
will introduce before long.
But for now, we have
the mechanisms in place
where we can do some
really interesting things.
So in fact, I thought, in the spirit
of thinking back on olden times,
thought I'd open up the very first
program I wrote when I actually took--
I was cross-registered
in an MIT class and took
a class that introduced
aspiring teachers to Scratch.
And I implemented this
program here called Oscartime,
which was a game that used a
childhood song that I was a fan of
and it allows you to drag
trash into a trash can.
But to bring this to life and perhaps
in exchange for one stress ball,
could I get one brave volunteer who
wants to come up and control this here
keyboard?
I saw your hand first.
Come on up.
And you'll see, thanks to the team, we
also have this amazing lamppost here,
being on Quincy Street as we are.
Do you want to introduce
yourself to the group?
AUDIENCE: Hi, my name is Anna.
I'm from Richmond,
Virginia, and I'm in Weld.
DAVID MALAN: Nice.
Weld.
AUDIENCE: Yes!
DAVID MALAN: All right, come on over.
So here, Anna, you'll
have a chance to play
the very first game I wrote
in Scratch, which admittedly
is more complicated
typically than we would
expect of a student doing this for the
very first time, as in problem set zero.
But what I'm going to do
is full screen this here.
I'm going to click the green flag,
and what you'll see on the screen
are these instructions.
Drag as much falling trash as you can to
Oscar's trashcan before his song ends.
And here we go.
[OSCAR THE GROUCH, "I LOVE TRASH"]
Oh, I love trash
Anything dirty or dingy or dusty
Anything ragged or rotten or rusty
Yes, I love trash
DAVID MALAN: There we go.
So as Anna continues to play, let's
tease this apart a little bit.
So one, there's some
costumes on the stage.
Like that lamppost is
actually never going to move.
But there's a couple of sprites.
There's the trash can, which seems
to be a character unto itself.
There's this piece of trash
that keeps coming back and back.
That is a sprite.
There's now this sneaker,
which is another sprite.
And in fact, notice that Oscar, of
course, keeps popping up from his sprite
once in a while.
So Oscar seems to have
multiple costumes.
So I offer this as an example, as
you keep playing, if you would.
Very good job so far.
The song goes on forever.
This was a nightmare to implement,
to listen to this all day long.
But how do we implement
the rest of this?
Well, notice that the trash, every
time she throws into the trash can,
does reappear somewhere different.
So there's some kind
of randomness involved.
And indeed, Scratch will let you
pick random numbers in a range.
So maybe it could be
negative 240, maybe it
could be positive 240, at the 180
point on the top of the screen.
So you can randomly put
things on the screen.
There's apparently
what kind of construct
that makes the trash
fall again and again.
I think no one's listening to me.
They're all just watching you.
What's making the trash
fall from top to bottom?
So it's actually some kind of loop
because there's a motion block
inside of a forever
loop, probably, that just
keeps moving the trash one pixel, one
pixel, one pixel, one pixel, one pixel,
creating the illusion,
therefore, of motion.
And if we can crank the
song a little bit more,
you'll see that this is
all synchronized now.
OSCAR THE GROUCH: (SINGING)
Because they're trash
Oh, I love trash
Anything dirty or dingy or dusty
Anything ragged--
DAVID MALAN: The song keeps
going forever, seemingly.
And now notice more and more sprites
are appearing because they waited for--
here we go.
Climax.
OSCAR THE GROUCH: (SINGING) I love trash
DAVID MALAN: All right.
A big round of applause for Anna.
Nicely done.
OK, here you go.
Here you go.
All right.
So this is an interminable song.
And indeed, I spent hours building that,
and just listening to that song on loop
was not the best way to program.
But the goal here is to really use it as
just an intellectual exercise as to how
that was implemented.
And we won't do the
entire thing in detail,
because I will say back in
the day when I was younger,
I didn't necessarily
write the cleanest code.
And in fact, if we see inside this and
we poke around the bottom of the screen
here, you can see all
of my different sprites.
And the code is kind of complex.
Like, things just kind
of escalated quickly.
But I did not set out and
write all of these programs
all at once for each sprite.
I pretty much took baby
steps, so to speak.
And so, for instance, let me open up
just a few sample building blocks here
that speak to this that
are written in advance.
So here's version zero.
Computer scientists typically
start counting at zero.
And let me show you this example here
that only has two sprites on the screen.
We have Oscar the trashcan and
we have the piece of trash.
And now notice, what does Oscar do?
Well, let me go ahead and zoom in
on this script, as it's called.
A program is a script.
When the green flag is clicked, Oscar
switches his costume to Oscar one.
That's his default costume
where the lid is closed.
Then Oscar does this forever.
If Oscar is touching the mouse pointer,
change the costume to Oscar two,
otherwise change it back to Oscar one.
So that whole idea of animation
where Oscar is popping in and out
is just like a quick
costume change based
on a loop inside of which is a
conditional waiting for the cursor,
like Anna did, to get
near the trash can.
Meanwhile, if we look at
the piece of trash here,
notice that the trash is actually not
doing anything in this first version
because I didn't even
implement falling first.
So let me hit the green flag.
Nothing is happening in
this very first version.
But notice, if I click on the trash
and drag as soon as I'm touching Oscar,
there comes that trash can lid.
And it was just the result of making
this one program respond to that input.
All right.
What did I do next?
Well, next, after taking that single
baby step, I added one other feature.
Let's see inside this version one.
Again, Oscar is behaving
the exact same way.
But notice this time the trash
is designed to do the following.
First, I'm telling the program
that the drag mode is draggable.
That is, I want the trash to be
movable when the user clicks on it.
Then I tell the piece of trash
to go to a random x location.
x is the horizontal, so it's
going somewhere between 0 and 240,
but all the way at
the top of the screen.
180.
Then forever, the piece of trash
just changes by negative one.
So it just moves down and down and down.
And without looking at the second
script yet, let me just hit play.
And notice, without even doing
anything-- and eventually,
once there was lots
of trash falling, like
Anna was struggling
to keep up with this.
It's just moving one pixel at a
time forever until, thankfully, MIT
does stop things automatically if they
hit the bottom, lest a six-year-old get
upset that all of a sudden
their sprite is gone forever.
So there is some special casing there.
But what else is this trash doing?
Let me zoom in here.
The piece of trash also, when
the green flag is clicked,
is forever asking this question.
If you are touching Oscar, then pick a
new random location between 0 and 240
at positive 180 and go back to the top.
So in other words, as soon
as this piece of trash
is dragged over to Oscar like this and I
let go, it recreates itself at the top.
It's just sort of teleporting to the
top, and thus was born this feature.
And I won't slog through all of
the individual features here,
but if we do just one more and see
inside this one-- so now let me go ahead
and hit Play.
Notice at the top left of
the screen, there's a score.
Currently zero.
But now when I click
the trash and let go,
notice that the score is
being incremented by one.
And this, in fact, is
how, Anna, your score kept
going higher and higher and higher.
Every time I noticed, oh, the trash is
touching Oscar, let's not only teleport,
let's also increment a variable.
And we didn't see this before, but
if I go to this Oscar Scratch now,
you'll see that it is exactly the same.
But if I now go to the trash piece here
and we go to when green flag clicked,
you'll see that I'm initializing a
variable in orange called score to zero.
But if we scroll down
to the bottom, Oscar
is also doing another thing
in parallel at the same time.
When the green flag is clicked,
Oscar is forever checking,
is the piece of trash touching Oscar?
If so, change the score
by one and then go to top,
which is another location
on there, that screen.
So in other words, even though
at a glance something like Oscar
time might look very complicated
and it did take me hours,
the goal, especially
with problem set zero,
is not going to be to bite
off all of that at once,
but to take proverbial baby steps.
Implement one tiny feature so that
you feel like you're making progress.
Add another feature, another.
And invariably you might
run out of time and not
get to the best version of your
vision, but hopefully it'll be good.
Hopefully it'll be better, but you'll
have these sort of mental milestones,
hoping that you at
least get to that point.
Because as you will soon discover,
everything in the world of programming
unfortunately takes longer
than you might expect.
That was true for me 25 years
ago and is still true today.
Well, let me introduce one
final set of examples here.
This one written by one of your
own predecessors, a former student.
Let me go ahead and open up
three baby steps, if you will,
toward an end of implementing a game
called Ivy's Hardest Game, whereby
it's now more interactive,
quite like Oscartime.
So at top right here,
notice-- and I'll zoom
in-- we have this world
that's initially very simple.
Two black lines, two walls, if you will,
and a Harvard sprite in the middle.
But when you click
the green flag, notice
that nothing happens initially except
that the sprite jumps to the middle.
But I can hit the up key or the down
key or the left key or the right key.
But if I try to go too far, even
though it's not the edge of the world,
it's only touching that there black
line, it's still going to stop as well.
So intuitively, how could you
implement that type of program?
How could you get a sprite from what
we've seen to respond to up, down, left,
right, but actually move
when I touch my arrow keys?
Like, what does it mean to move?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: Maybe if then.
DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
So much like with representing
information, at the end of the day,
all we've got is zeros and ones.
When it comes to
algorithms, at the moment,
all we have are functions
and loops and conditionals
and Boolean expressions and
soon some more things too.
But there's not all that
much we have at our disposal.
So let me zoom out from this
and let me actually show you
what the Harvard sprite is doing.
It's doing this.
When I go up to the green flag here,
the Harvard sprite is going to 0, 0.
So dead center in the middle.
And then it's forever doing two
things, listening for the keyboard
and feeling for walls, left and right.
Now, those are not puzzle
pieces that come with Scratch.
I created my own custom blocks, my own
functions to implement those ideas.
Let's not abstract away for now.
Let's actually look at these features.
And indeed, to your
instincts at left here,
what does it mean to
listen for the keyboard?
Well, if the up arrow key
is pressed, change y by one.
Move up.
If the down arrow key is pressed,
change y by negative one.
If the right arrow key is
pressed, change x by one.
If the left arrow key is pressed,
change x by negative one.
So take all the magic
out of moving up, down,
left, right by just quantizing it
as plus, minus, this, and that.
It's all numbers, indeed,
at the end of the day.
But what else is it doing?
Notice that it did, indeed,
bounce off the wall.
So my other custom
function, which I chose,
feel for walls to evoke this
idea, it's asking two questions.
If you're touching the left
wall, then change x by one,
so bounce in the other direction.
Else if you're touching the right wall,
bounce in the negative one direction.
And so what are left
wall and right wall?
I mean, I kind of cheated.
I just used two more sprites.
These sprites are literally
nothing except black lines.
But because they exist, I can ask that
question in my conditional saying,
are you touching those other sprites?
And I could have colored them any way I
want, but this is enough, if I zoom in,
to implement this idea of going
up, down, left, and right,
and preventing the sprite from
leaving that little world.
All right.
So if you'll agree that there's
a way now to implement motion up,
down, left, right, let's go
ahead and implement this idea
by adding a rival into the
mix, like a Yale sprite.
And what the Yale sprite is going to
do, if I click the green flag, is this.
So Harvard at the moment is still going
to be movable with the arrow keys,
up, down, left, right.
But Yale, for better
or for worse, is just
going to mindlessly bounce back and
forth from left to right forever,
it would seem.
The operative word being forever.
So how is that working?
Well, let's look.
Here's the Yale sprite at the bottom.
Let's zoom in on its actual code here.
The Yale sprite starts at 0, 0.
It points in direction 90 degrees,
which means left, right, essentially.
And then it forever does this.
If touching the left wall or touching
the right wall, turn around 180 degrees.
So I don't want the
Yale sprite to just stop
by moving it one pixel
to bounce off slightly.
I want it to wrap around and just keep
going and going and going forever.
And that's it.
Everything else is the same.
So one final flourish.
Let's add a more formidable
adversary, like MIT here,
whereby if I zoom in
and hit play, notice
that if I move the Harvard
sprite, MIT comes chasing me now.
Now, how is this actually working?
Yale is just kind of doing its
thing, bouncing back and forth.
Now MIT has really latched on to me and
it's following me up, down, left, right.
So how is that logic now working?
Well, again, it's probably
doing something forever,
because that's why it's
continually doing it.
Let's click on MIT.
This too is pretty simple, even
though it's a pretty fancy idea.
Initially the MIT sprite
goes to a random position,
but thereafter, it forever points
toward the Harvard logo outline, which
is just the long name that your
predecessor or former student
gave the name for that sprite.
And then it moves one
step, one step, one step.
So suppose this were an actual
game, and in games things
get harder and harder, the
adversary moves faster and faster.
How could we make MIT even faster
by changing just one thing here?
Like, how do we level up?
Change the one to two pixels
at a time, two steps at a time.
So let's see that.
Let's go ahead and zoom out.
Let's hit play.
And now notice that MIT is
coming in much faster this time.
All right.
So it wasn't noticeably faster.
Let's do this.
Let's move 10 steps at a time.
So 10 steps faster than originally.
I mean, now-- and now notice it's kind
of twitching back and forth in this way.
Why?
Well, probably, if we worked
out the math, probably
the MIT sprite is touching the
sprite and it's bouncing off of it,
but then it's realizing,
oh, I went too far.
Let me move back.
Wait a minute.
I'm still touching it.
Let me move down.
So you can get into
these perverse situations
where there is actually a bug,
be it logical or aesthetical.
But in this case, we
probably want to fix that.
So 10 is probably too fast for
this to work particularly well.
But the final flourish here really is
to show you the actual version of a game
that one of your predecessors, a
past classmate, actually implemented.
Before, thereafter, we
will adjourn for cake
in the transept, which
is the CS50 tradition.
But can we get one more
final volunteer to come on
up to play Ivy's Hardest Game?
I'm seeing your hand most
enthusiastically there.
Yeah, come on down.
Very happily.
[APPLAUSE]
In just a moment, we
will indeed adjourn.
But the goal here now is going
to be to navigate a maze that's
a little more difficult than the last.
Let's have you first, though, introduce
yourselves to your classmates in front.
AUDIENCE: Hi, y'all.
I'm Eric.
I'm from Philadelphia and
I'm also from Hollis Hall.
[CHEERS]
DAVID MALAN: One person from Hollis.
Nice.
OK.
Welcome.
All right.
Eric, go ahead and
take the keyboard here.
It, too, will be all about
up, down, left, right as soon
as you click the green flag.
And if we can crank the music.
[MC HAMMER, "U CAN'T TOUCH THIS"]
You Can't touch this
DAVID MALAN: So notice, the black
walls are a little more involved
than last time.
But the goal is to get to the
sprite all the way at right
and just touch it, at which
point you move to the next level.
The next level, of course, has Yale
doing its thing back and forth.
You've made it to level three.
But now there's two Yale.
So another sprite is in
the mix that's randomly
moving a little different
in terms of direction.
Three Yales.
Next level.
MIT is in.
Nice.
The walls are now gone.
Princeton's in the mix.
Nice.
Two Princetons.
OK.
New life.
OK, another life.
Nice.
Oh.
Second to last level.
Three Princetons.
Last level.
Yeah!
Congratulations.
[APPLAUSE]
Thank you.
All right.
This, then, was CS50.
Welcome aboard.
Cake is now served.
[MUSIC PLAYING]